In this lesson, we're going to start with the email agent that we created previously.
And we're going to add in tools to allow to operate on semantic memory.
Now as a reminder, semantic memory normally stores facts about a user.
So we're going to use these tools to learn facts about users.
We're then going to store them in a long-term memory store.
And then we're going to add a separate tool to search over these facts.
Let's see it in code.
So here we have a lot of setup from the previous lesson.
And this should look all the same.
We're going to load some environment variables.
We're going to define our profile.
We're going to define our prompt instructions.
In example, email, we're going to set up the router, nothing's changed here.
We're going to import some prompts.
We're going to define our three tools that we had before.
Now we're going to start to define our tools for managing memory.
The first thing we're going to want to do is properly set up our long-term memory store.
And so for this lesson, we're just going to use an in-memory store, a store that will
store everything in memory.
And so we're going to import that from LaneGraph.
When we initialize it, we're going to want to make sure that we pass in this index
program.
Here we're passing in an embedding model to use to index the memories that we store.
So we're going to use the OpenAI Text Embedding 3 small model.
Afterwards, we're going to import two functions from LaneMem.
LaneMem is a wrapper on top of LaneGraph for working with memory.
These two functions are going to be called Create Manage Memory Tool and Create Search
Memory Tool.
And these will be tools from managing and searching over memories.
To create them, it's pretty simple.
We're just going to define the namespace that we want these tools to operate on.
So the namespace that we're going to use for both is email assistant as the first value.
Then this templated LaneGraph user ID, and I'll come back to that as a second value, and
then collection as the third value.
So what exactly is this?
When we invoke the agent now, we're going to pass in a LaneGraph user ID as part of the
runtime configuration.
And that's going to be used to namespace this memory.
That way, if we're dealing with emails from multiple users, we can pretty easily just
have different collections of memories for different users.
We wouldn't want them to be the same.
And so here's where we define that we store them separately.
Because these are just LaneChain tools, we can inspect them and see what attributes
they have.
So they should have a name, so we can see that managed memory tools name is called
managed memory.
They should also probably have a description.
So we can see that this is the description of how to use the tool.
Let's print it out to make it a little bit more legible.
Here we can see that it contains instructions for creating, updating, or deleting persistent
memories.
We can also take a look at the arguments to this tool.
We can see that it takes in content, then an action, so the action can be create, update,
or delete, and then an ID.
And so basically what's happening is these memories are managed by IDs.
And so when we call to this tool, we can pass in the ID of a memory, the action we want
to take on it, whether we should update it or create it or delete it.
And then the content of that memory as well.
If we look at the search memory tool, we can see that it's called search memory.
The description is pretty simple, just search your long-term memories for information
relevant to your current context.
And the arguments are also pretty simple, it's just to query a limit for the number of
memories that we want to return, some offset, and then some filter if we want.
Let's now go on to define the agent.
Here we're going to take the agent system prompt, and we're actually going to modify it
a little bit, because now we need to add in these two extra tools.
So this is slightly modified from the previous lesson.
We're still going to have the similar create prompt function, which basically creates this
some message and appends it before the list of messages in the state.
After that, we can build our agent as normal.
We'll import this create react agent function.
We'll create our list of tools, which now contains this manage memory tool and the search
memory tool.
And then we'll create our react agent, which we'll now call response agent, and notice
that we're also passing in the store to ensure that this is passed to the agent.
Let's now test the agent.
The first thing we're going to want to do is actually define a config that we're going
to pass to the agent with some runtime configuration, and it's going to have to have this
Langrath user ID.
So let's create that first.
You can change this value, which I'm calling Lance, to be anything you want.
Let's now call it with a message that has some information that we should probably
remember, like Jim is my friend.
And notice here, I'm passing in the config as a second parameter.
Let's take a look at the response.
If we print out the list of messages, we can see that we have the human message, which
we pass in.
And then we have the say I message.
It calls the manage memory tool with the arguments content, Jim is John Doe's friend.
Notice that we're not specifying in action because the default is to create, and we're
not specifying an ID, because it will create one by default.
We get back a message that we created this memory with this user ID, and then the final
message is that it's just recorded this information about Jim.
Let's try this with another input.
Let's ask now who is Jim, and notice that we're passing in the same config as before.
Let's take a look at the list of messages that we get back as a response.
Who is Jim, this is our user message.
We then get a message from the AI, which calls a tool, it calls a search memory tool, with
a query parameter of Jim.
We get back this list of messages.
In this case, we only have one message, which is this namespace memory at this value.
This key is the ID, and then the content is Jim is John Doe's friend.
Then we get back a response from the AI message that summarizes the above interaction.
So it says, based on my memory search, I can see that Jim is John Doe's friend.
If we want to inspect the stored directly, we can.
We can call list namespaces, and we can see that this one namespace exists.
And remember, this is the template that we defined above, where this is the link
graph user ID, and we passed in lance for that value.
If we now call search on this namespace, we can see the different items that exist there.
So we can see that we only have one item, because we've only remembered one piece of information,
and its value has this content Jim is John Doe's friend.
Notice the score here is none.
That's because we haven't passed in a query parameter.
Let's pass one in, and let's see what the score is.
If we pass in a query of Jim, we can now see that the score is 0.5 something.
The score is calculated as cosine similarity using the embedding model that we passed
in when we created the store in the first place.
That was a good time to pause, use this response agent directly, try querying it with different
things after to see if it remembers, and you can also inspect the store itself.
Now let's go on to creating the rest of the agent.
So this should all look very similar to the previous lesson, because not much is changing.
We've mostly just added these tools to the response agent.
So first we're creating the state, this is the same as before.
We're making some imports, same as before.
We're creating this triage router node, same as before.
We then create the email agent.
This is the same as before, with two changes.
First, I've changed this to be response agent.
So before previous lesson two, this was called agent, I've just updated the variable name
and so it's changed here, nothing big.
But next, I'm going to change the compile step.
So I'm going to pass in store equals store when I create the email agent.
This is giving it access to that long-term memory store that our memory tools are going
to use.
If I display the email agent, I get the same graph as before, so nothing's changed here.
I can create this example email input.
And then when I call the email agent, this is now also going to change slightly.
I'm going to remember to pass in my configuration.
This contains the lane graph user ID that we will use in the memory tools.
We can see that it runs and that it first classifies that it should respond and then it continues
down that path.
Once it's finished, let's take a look at the list of messages that are in the agent's
trajectory so we can see what it does.
So the first message there is a human message.
This is the input of the email.
We then get back an AI message where it's writing an email.
So it has a tool call with this right email and it's passing in all these arguments and
so you can see the content of the email that it writes here.
We then get back a tool message saying that it sent that email successfully.
We then call the I message again and we see that it calls the managed memory tool and
it creates this memory with this content.
Follow up needed.
Alice Smith has inquired about missing API endpoints.
We get back a tool message that it created that memory and then we get back the final
response from the agent that it's taken two actions.
It's sent a response to Alice and it's created a memory entry.
So this is the agent with the semantic tools in place.
Let's try out another example that requires some of the memory that was saved as part
of this previous email.
So let's pass in this new email from Alice Smith as well, so same author and it says
hi John, any update on my previous ask.
When we invoke it, we can see that it correctly classifies it as an email that it needs
a response to and it continues from there.
Let's take a look at the agent trajectory.
So we can see that we have the human message with the new email and we can see that it
now first calls the search memory tool with this query Alice Smith previous requests to
ask communication.
So it's trying to figure out what information it has.
It gets back this memory that it saved before.
We can see it's logic and then it calls this right email tool and it writes this email
and we can see that in its responses as thanks for following up regarding the API endpoints
documentation.
So this is remembered from before even though it's a completely separate email.
We can see the tool message that it sent a response to Alice and then we can see the
final response.
This is an example of how you can see that the memory tools are saving relevant information
and then also searching over it in the future.
This is it for this lesson.
So now is a great time to pause and spend a few more minutes playing around with different
emails, trying out different questions and seeing if they can remember different facts.
See you in the next lesson.